Finding Aid for the Charles Appy Papers PASC-M.0108
UCLA Library Special Collections
Charles Appy papers
circa 1824-1934
UCLA Library Special Collections
Appy, Charles Ernest
PASC-M.0108
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
This collection consists of correspondence and musical excerpts.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303273606533
Biography
Charles Ernest Appy was a musician, composer, teacher, and founder of two music schools. Born in 1834 of French parents in The Hague, Netherlands, Appy moved with his family as a child to Amsterdam, where he studied piano with Richard Hol, cello with Charles Montigny and Merlen, and composition with Jacques Franco-Mendes. In 1851 he became cellist in the concert orchestra at Zaandam. In 1854 he performed as a solo cellist in Scotland. Two years later he became a member of the Amsterdam Park Orchestra and of the orchestra of the Felix Meritis Society. In 1857 he assisted with the concerts at London's Crystal Palace. He returned to Amsterdam to join the orchestra of the Caecilia Society in Amsterdam. He began playing in a string quartet in 1862. He served as cello teacher at the Maatschappij tot Bevordering van Toonkunst from 1864-83. He opened schools of music in Amsterdam and in Kansas City. His compositions for cello include Phantasies on themes from Der freischütz and Robert der Teufel, as well as small salon pieces. He died in 1895.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence from Hans von Bülow, Clara Schumann, Franz Liszt, Niels Gade, Stephen Heller, Carl Hill, Salomon Jadassohn, Karl Hermann, Beethoven, and others, as well as musical excerpts from Hans von Bülow, Leander Schlegel, B. Kwast, Woldemar Bargiel, Ernst S. Rabitzky, and others.
Composers -- Netherlands -- Correspondence.; Appy, Charles Ernest--Archives.
- Letter from Hans von Bulow, November 8 (Box 1, Item 1)
- Letter from Clara Schumann, 1860 (Box 1, Item 2)
- Letter from Franz Liszt, 1876 May 5 (Box 1, Item 3)
- Letter from Niels Gade, 1873 October 2 (Box 1, Item 4)
- Letter from Stephen Heller, 1861 [?] May 26 (Box 1, Item 5)
- Letter from Carl Hill, 1872 [?] June 4 (Box 1, Item 6)
- Letter from Salomon Jadassohn, 1888 February 28 (Box 1, Item 7)
- Letter [signature indecipherable], 1883 April 9 (Box 1, Item 8)
- Letter from Karl Herrman, 1876 September 20 (Box 1, Item 9)
- Letter [signature indecipherable], 1888 [?] November 13 (Box 1, Item 10)
- Musical excerpt by August Wilhelmj, 1866 April 27 (Box 1, Item 11)
- Musical excerpt and note from Hans von Bulow, 1865 March 21 (Box 1, Item 12)
- Musical excerpt from Julius Röntgen, 1879 December 5 (Box 1, Item 13)
- Musical excerpt and note from Leander Schlegel, 1865 August [?] 15 (Box 1, Item 14)
- Musical excerpt and note from B. Kwast, 1879 January 17 (Box 1, Item 15)
- Musical excerpt and note from Woldemar Bargiel, no date (Box 1, Item 16)
- Musical excerpt by G. Bartel, no date (Box 1, Item 17)
- Excerpt from Hungarian Dance, by Ernst S. Rabitzky, 18[??] December 27 (Box 1, Item 18)
- Quotation of Confucius, in Chinese and German, written by G. Schlegel [?], 1872 October 17 (Box 1, Item 19)
- Lottery ticket, owned by G. A. Franck, 1860 June 2 (Box 1, Item 20)
- Pencil Sketch and greeting from E. Koster [?], 1877 October 25 (Box 1, Item 21)
- Message on card, very faded, signature indecipherable, 1860 December 9 (Box 1, Item 22)
- Note signed by Beethoven, 1824 May [?] 20 (Box 1, Item 23)
- A New York Girl's Wonderful Autograph Manuscripts, no date (Box 1, Item 24)
- Letter from Carl Trill, 1901 September 9 (Box 1, Item 25)
- Excerpt in German from the book The Violoncello and Its History, 1934 June 21 (Box 1, Item 26)
  Scope and Content
  Biographical information on Charles Ernest Appy.
- English translation of the contents of Item 26, no date (Box 1, Item 27)
- Letter from Concert Direction of Daniel Mayer (London), 1894 August 28 (Box 1, Item 28)
- Cartoon of instrumentalists, no date (Box 1, Item 29)
- Membership certificate from the Derthick Federation of Musical-Literary Clubs, 1896 December 22 (Box 1, Item 30)
- Certificate awarded Ernest Appy by the Prince of the Netherlands, April 11 (Box 1, Item 31)
- Concerts given in England and Europe, 1857-1864 (Box 1, Item 32)